Guide to Kenneth Horwitz Beaumont [TX] Jewish congregation materials, 1952-1987 MS 801
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Kenneth Horwitz Beaumont [TX] Jewish congregation materials
1952-1987
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Horwitz, W. Kenneth, Dr.
MS 801
.25 Linear Feet 1 box
The collection consists of one box of event materials, a booklet about the history of Beaumont Texas, and four photographs.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Horwitz is a native of Beaumont, Texas. He attended the University of Texas at Austin and in 1961, graduated from the University of Texas Dental Branch at Houston, where, after serving two years in the Air Force, he held a clinical appointment in Operative Dentistry and Endodontics. Dr. Horwitz has been in full- time private practice in Houston throughout his career.
Dr. Horwitz's parents, Dora Adler Horwitz and Joe Horwitz, and his mother's siblings, Ben Adler and Eva Adler Swerdlow, ran Adler's clothing store for decades in downtown Beaumont, Texas. The store was started by Dr. Horwitz's grandparents in 1913 and closed in 1991.
Temple Emanuel was founded in Beaumont in 1895 and erected its first building in 1901. Congregation Kol Israel was founded in 1917 by members who preferred Orthodoxy to the Reform worship style at Temple Emanuel. Due to dwindling numbers, the two Congregations merged in 1971, at which time and Kol Israel constructed a separate chapel in the Sunday school building of the Temple Emanuel complex. Due to this merger, Temple Emanuel grew from 175 contributing members in 1970 to 223 in 1976. The family belonged to Congregation Kol Israel prior to 1971 and continued at Temple Emanuel. Temple Emanuel is the only Synagogue that remains in Southeast Texas. Unfortunately, the Jewish community in Beaumont, like many rural Jewish communities around the country, has declined in recent years and left Temple Emanuel's future uncertain.
Excerpted from:
https://www.ddshouston.com/our-practice/dr-w-kenneth-horwitz/ http://www.isjl.org/texas-beaumont-encyclopedia.html
Scope and Contents
One box of materials (programs and booklets) from events in Beaumont, including Congregation Emanuel and Congregation Kol Israel, an ethnic history of Beaumont, and photographs of Horwitz's family members and groups from Kol Israel between the years 1952 and 1987. Of particular significance is a photo of Horwitz's mother, uncle, and aunt inside Adler's clothing store in Beaumont and event programs from the now merged Congregation Kol Israel.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been arranged chronologically in one series as follows:
Series I: General
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Dr. W. Kenneth Horwitz donated the materials in October of 2018.
Index Terms
Subjects
Religion; Jews and Jewish life; Social life and customs
Document Types
programs (documents); photographs; booklets
Subjects (Persons)
Horwitz, W. Kenneth, Dr.
- Series I: General, 1952-1987
  - Group photographs (2), Congregation Kol Israel, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Mitzvah Donor - sisterhood Kol Israel program, 1964-11-29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Congregation Kol Israel 50th Anniversary Golden Jubilee Celebration program and book, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - An Evening Dedicated to Area Banks and Financial Institutions, featuring Henny Youngman program (signed by Henny Youngman), 1967-05-28 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Temple Emanuel 75th Anniversary program, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs (2) Adler's Department Store (Dora Adler Horwitz, Ben Adler, Eva Adler Swerdlow), c. 1970's-1980's (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Celebrate Beaumont Sesquicentennial program, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Centennial Celebration of the Jewish Community of Beaumont, Texas programs, 1987-10-17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Portrait of a People: An Ethnic History of Beaumont Texas" booklet, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)